Hi!
There are many reasons why a budget might fail or why people give up on their budget but drawing up a budget is usually pure drudgery and livened only by the reality of staring your foolish spending habits in your face.
In fact one of the chief impediments of budgeting is that most people would rather not know how they really use the money.
Take heart any spending mistakes you are making are probably common and not impossible to kick.
More over the bulk of budgeting paints happen at the beginning.
After you have a budget in place and you have fine tuned it with a couple of months of actual spending, tracking your expenditures become almost automatic.
A lot of people have unrealistic projections.
If you are determined to make a budget work, then you've got to be realistic.
You've got to be honest with yourself is the first step.
Are you really willing to give up certain items like dining in or buying the latest DVD movie.
It might more realistic to cut back on the amount you spend rather to attempt totally removing these kinds of expenses from your budget plan.
You can reduce the amount you spend in these items rather than trying to totally eliminate these luxuries.
It is often said if you fail to plan, you plan to fail.
A written budget will not only help you keep on track, but will also help you to evaluate where your budget needs to be revised.
Start a written plan for each month.
Know that budgets are fluid.
At the end of 3 months evaluate how well your budget worked or what adjustments are needed.
Some items get forgotten and aren't placed in your budget.
For example, gifts for birthdays, graduations, weddings, showers.
These are some of the big items that don't make the budget list but which will also throw budgeting into chaos.
Other forgotten items include car insurance, professional association or club dues, subscription and Internet fees and other kinds of expenses which show up only periodically or annually.
The solution to this problem is to pull out the calendar and list what kinds of special occasions will be coming up in the next 3 to 6 months.
Set a price range for gift purchases rather than shopping impulsively.
Annual costs such as dues, subscription fees and car insurance and divide them out by 12.
Keep a running tally of all annual costs and check periodically as costs go up or down for each item.